<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Contemplations upon life and death with serious reflections on the miseries that attend humane life in every station, degree and change thereof / written by a person of quality in his confinement a little before his death ... a true copy of the paper delivered to the sheriffs upon the scaffold at Tower-hill on Thursday, January 28, 1696/7 by Sir John Fenwick, Baronet.</title>
            <author>Fenwick, John, Sir, 1645?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37797</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17020066</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17020066</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105818</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105818)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1615:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Contemplations upon life and death with serious reflections on the miseries that attend humane life in every station, degree and change thereof / written by a person of quality in his confinement a little before his death ... a true copy of the paper delivered to the sheriffs upon the scaffold at Tower-hill on Thursday, January 28, 1696/7 by Sir John Fenwick, Baronet.</title>
                  <author>Fenwick, John, Sir, 1645?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G. Larkin and sold by most booksellers ..,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fenwick, John, --  Sir, 1645?-1697.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105818:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONTEMPLATIONS UPON Life and Death: WITH Serious Reflections on the Miſeries THAT ATTEND HUMANE LIFE, In every Station, Degree, and Change thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by a Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ality, in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement, a lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fore his Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SHEWING The Vanity of the Deſires of Long LIFE, and the Fears of DEATH.</p>
            <p>WITH A True Copy of the PAPER Delivered to the Sheriffs upon the Scaffold at <hi>Tower-Hill,</hi> on <hi>Thurſday, January</hi> 28. 1696/7</p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>JOHN FENWICK,</hi> Baronet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>G. Larkin,</hi> and Sold by moſt Bookſellers in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtmiſtſter.</hi> 1697.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105818:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105818:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105818:3"/>
            <head>Contemplations upon <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death;</hi> WITH <hi>Serious Reflections on the Miſeries that attend Humane Life, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oſce te ipſum,</hi> is a Leſſon a Man can never learn too late: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tho' hitherto I have liv'd ſo much a Stranger to my ſelf, that I have had little leiſure, and leſs deſire, to think or to Contemplate, (a ſtudious and ſedentary Life ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving always been my Averſion) yet the Solitary Condition I am now reduc'd to, and the Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Circumſtances under which I lie, do methinks call upon me to conſider what I have been doing, and what I am further ſhortly to do: I am now under a cloſe Confinement, ſecluded from all Coverſation with the World, and deny'd the Viſits of my Neareſt and Deareſt Relations; And all this ſeems to be but the ſad Prologue to that ſadder Tragedy in which I am to be the principal Actor, before I go off the Stage of this World. And therefore ſince Death and I muſt ſhortly be better acquainted, it will certainly be my Wiſdom, as well as my Intereſt, to familiarize it to me before-hand: And I do not know
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105818:4"/>how that can be better done, than by contemplating the Miſeries of Life, in all its various Changes and Conditions; and then to look upon Death as the great <hi>Panpharmacon,</hi> and Remedy of all thoſe Evils that Life ſubjects us to.</p>
            <p>'Tis true indeed, we generally fly from Death as our worſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, altho' it is in truth our greateſt Friend; and this, to a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Man, is very unaccountable. I muſt confeſs it does ſeem ſtrange to me, and is methinks a thing to be admir'd, that the poor Labourer to repoſe himſelf longs for the ſetting Sun; that the Mariner rows with all his might to attain his wiſh'd-for Port, and rejoyces when he can diſcover Land; that the Traveller is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver contented till he be at the end of his Journey: And that we, in the mean while, tied in this World to a perpetual Task, toſs'd with continual Tempeſts, and tired with a rough and thorny way, yet cannot ſee the end of our Labour, but with grief; nor behold our Port, but with tears; nor approach to our Home, but with horrour and trembling. This Life is but a <hi>Penelope</hi>'s Web, in which we are always doing and undoing; a Sea that lies open to all Winds, which ſometimes within, and ſometimes without, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ceaſes to blow violently upon us; a weary Journey through extream heats and colds, over high Mountains, ſteep Rocks, and dangerous Deſarts: And thus we paſs away our time in weaving at this Web; in rowing at this Oar, and in paſſing this miſerable Way: And yet when Death comes to end our Work, and ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es out his Arms to pull us into the Port; when after ſo many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Paſſages, and loathſome Lodgings, he would conduct us to our true Home and Reſting Place; inſtead of rejoycing at the end of our Labour, of taking comfort at the ſight of our deſired Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and of ſinging at our approach to thoſe happy Manſions; we would fain begin our Work again, hoiſe Sail to the Wind, and would willingly undertake our Journey anew: No more we then remember our wearineſs and pains; our dangers and our ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracks are forgotten: We fear no more the tireſomeneſs of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, nor the danger of Deſarts. But on the contrary, we appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend Death as an extream pain; we ſhun it as the fatal Rock on which we are like to ſplit; we fly it as a Thief that comes to rob us of our Treaſure: We do as little Children, who all the day complain of Illneſs, and when the Medicine is brought them, are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105818:4"/>no longer ſick: Or as they who all the week long run up and down the ſtreets, complaining of the pain of their Teeth, and yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Barber coming to pull them out, are rather willing ſtill to endure the pain, than uſe the Remedy: And as thoſe tender and delicate Bodies, who in a pricking Pleuriſie complain, and cry out, and cannot ſtay for a Surgeon; and yet when they ſee him whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Launcet, to cut the throat of the Diſeaſe, pull in their Arms and hide them in the Bed, as if he were come to kill them. We fear more the Cure, than the Diſeaſe; the Surgeon, than the Pain; the Stroke, than the Impoſthume: We have more ſence of the Medicines bitterneſs, ſoon gone, than of a bitter long-conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Languiſhing: We have more feeling of Death, the End of our Miſeries, than the Endleſs Miſery of our Life. And whence proceedeth this Folly and Simplicity? We neither know Life nor Death: We fear what we ought to hope for, and wiſh for what we ought to fear: We call Life a continual Death, and yet Death is the Entrance of a Never-dying Life.</p>
            <p>Now what Good, O my Soul, is there in Life, that thou ſhouldſt ſo much deſire it? Or what evil is there in Death, that thou ſhouldſt ſo much fear it? Nay what Evil is there not in Life, and what Good is there not in Death?</p>
            <p>Conſider all the Periods of this Life: We enter it in tears, we paſs it in ſweat, we end it in ſorrow. Great and Little, Rich and Poor, not one in the whole World that can plead Immunity from this Condition. Man in this point is worſe than all other Creatures: He is born unable to ſupport himſelf; neither recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in his firſt years any pleaſure, nor giving to others any thing but trouble; and before the Age of Diſcretion paſſing infinite dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Onely herein he is leſs unhappy than in other Ages, becauſe in this he hath no ſence nor apprehenſion of his Miſery. Now can we think there is any ſo void of Reaſon, that if it were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to live always a Child, would make Choice of ſuch a Life?</p>
            <p>So then it is evident, That not ſimply <hi>to Live,</hi> is deſirable; but <hi>to Live Well and Happily.</hi> But to proceed.</p>
            <p>Grows he? His Troubles likewiſe grow up with him. Scarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is he come out of his Nurſes hands, and ſcarce knows what it is to play, but he falls under the ſubjection of a Schoolmaſter: I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105818:5"/>ſpeak but of thoſe which have the beſt Education, and are brought up with the greateſt care and ſtrictneſs. And then if he ſtudies, it is ever with Repining: And if he plays, it is never but with Fear.</p>
            <p>This whole Age, while he is under the charge of another, is unto him no better than a Priſon: And therefore he longs for, and only aſpires to that Age, in which, freed from the Tutelage of another, he may become Maſter of himſelf; puſhing Time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as it were, with his ſhoulder, that he may the ſooner enjoy his hoped-for Liberty. In ſhort, he deſires nothing more than to ſee the end of this Age, which he looks upon as Bondage and Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and enter upon the beginning of his Youth.</p>
            <p>And what is the beginning of Youth, but the death of Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? And the beginning of Manhood, but the death of Youth? Or what is the beginning of to Morrow, but the death of the preſent Day?</p>
            <p>And thus he implicitly deſires his Death, and judges his Life mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable; and therefore cannot be reputed in a ſtate of Happineſs or Contentment.</p>
            <p>Behold him now, according to his wiſh, at Liberty; in that Age wherein he has his Choice, to take the way of Vertue or of Vice, and either to chooſe Reaſon or Paſſion for his Guide: His Paſſion entertains him with a thouſand Delights, prepares for him a thouſand Baits, and preſents him with a thouſand Worldly Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to ſurprize him; And theſe are ſo agreeable to headſtrong and unbridled Youth, that there are very few that are not taken and beguiled by them; of which my own Example is too evident an Inſtance.</p>
            <p>But when the Reckoning comes to be made up, what Pleaſures are they? They are but vicious and polluted Pleaſures, which ever hold him in a reſtleſs Fever: Pleaſures that at the beſt end in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and like ſweet Meats, are of a hard digeſtion: Pleaſures that are bought with pain, and in a moment periſh, but leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind a laſting Guilt, and long remorſe of Conſcience: All which I wiſh my own too dear Experience could not witneſs.</p>
            <p>And yet this is the very Nature (if they be well examin'd) of all the Pleaſures of this World: There is in none ſo much Sweetneſs, but there is more Bitterneſs; none ſo pleaſant to the Mouth, but it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105818:5"/>leaves an unſavoury Guſto after it. I will not ſpeak here of the Miſchiefs, Quarrels, Debates, Wounds, Murthers, Baniſhments, Sickneſs and other Dangers, whereinto ſometimes the Incontinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and ſometimes the Inſolency of this ill-guided Age does plunge Men; for the remembrance of my own Follies upon this occaſion, ſtops my mouth, and fills me with remorſe and ſhame.</p>
            <p>But if thoſe that ſeem Pleaſures be nothing elſe but Diſpleaſures, if the Sweetneſs thereof be as an Infuſion of Wormwood; what then muſt the Diſpleaſure be which they feel? And how great the Bitterneſs that they taſte?</p>
            <p>Behold then in ſhort the Life of a young Man, who rid of the Government of his Parents and Maſters, abandons himſelf to all the Exorbitancies of his unruly Paſſion, which like an unclean Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit poſſeſſing him, throws him ſometimes into the Water, and then into the Fire; ſometimes carries him clear over a Rock, and at other times flings him headlong to the bottom.</p>
            <p>But if he follows <hi>Reaſon</hi> for his Guide (which is much the better choice) yet on this hand there are wonderful Difficulties: For he muſt reſolve to fight in every part of the Field, and at every ſtep to be in conflict, as having his Enemy in front, in flank, and on the rear, never leaving to aſſail him; and this Enemy is all that can delight him, all that he ſees near, or far off; In ſhort, the greateſt Enemy in the World is the World it ſelf, which he muſt therefore overcome: But beſide the World, he has a thouſand Treacherous Enemies within him, among whom his Paſſion is none of the leaſt, which waits for an occaſion to ſurprize him, and betray him to his Luſts. It is God only that can make him chooſe the Path of Vertue, and it is God only that can keep him in it to the End, and make him victorious in all his combats. But alas, how few they are that enter into it! And of thoſe few, how many that retire again! So that let a Man follow the one way or the other, he muſt either ſubject himſelf to a Tyrannical Paſſion, or undertake a weary and continual Combat; wilfully throw himſelf into the Arms of Deſtruction, or fetter himſelf as it were in the Stocks; eaſily carried away with the current of the Water, or painfully ſtemming the impetuous Tide.</p>
            <p>See here the happineſs of the young Man! Who in his Youth having drunk his full draught of the Worlds vain and deceivable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105818:6"/>Pleaſures, is over-taken by them with ſuch a dull heavineſs and aſtoniſhment, as Drunkards the morrow after a Debauch; or Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, after a plentiful Feaſt; who are ſo over-preſt with the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of the former day, that the very remembrance of it creates their loathing. And even he that has made the ſtouteſt reſiſtance, feels himſelf ſo weary, and with this continual Conflict ſo bruiſed and broken, that he is either upon the point to yield, or dye. And this is all the Good, all the Contentment of this flouriſhing Age, by Children ſo earneſtly deſired, and by thoſe who have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd it, ſo heartily lamented.</p>
            <p>Next cometh that which is called Perfect Age, in which Men have no other thoughts, but to purchaſe themſelves Wiſdom and Reſt. It is called perfect indeed, but is herein only perfect, that all Imperfections of Humane Nature, hidden before under the ſimplicity of Childhood, or the lightneſs of Youth, appear at this Age in their Perfection. I ſpeak of none in this place, but thoſe that are eſteemed the wiſeſt and moſt happy, in the opinion of the World.</p>
            <p>I have already ſhewed that we play'd in fear; and that our ſhort Pleaſures were attended on with long Repentance: But now Avarice and Ambition preſent themſelves to us, promiſing if we will adore them, to give us perfect Contentment with the Goods and Honours of this World; And ſurely none but thoſe who are reſtrained by a Divine Hand, can eſcape the Illuſions of the one or the other, and not caſt themſelves headlong from the top of the Pinacle.</p>
            <p>But let us ſee what this Contentment is: The Covetous Man Makes a thouſand Voyages by Sea, and Journeys by Land; runs a thouſand hazzards, eſcapes a thouſand ſhipwracks, and is in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual fear and travel; and yet oftentimes either loſeth his time, or gains nothing but Sickneſſes, Gouts and Oppilations. In the purchaſe of this goodly Repoſe, he beſtoweth his true Reſt; and to gain Wealth, loſeth his Life. But ſuppoſe he hath gain'd much, and that he hath ſpoil'd the whole Eaſt of its Pearls, and drawn dry all the Mines of the Weſt; will he then be at quiet, and ſay he is content? Nothing leſs: For by all his Acquiſitions, he gains but more Diſquiet both of Mind and Body; from one travel fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into another, never ending, but only changing his Miſeries:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105818:6"/>He deſir'd to have them, and now fears to loſe them; he got 'em with burning ardour, and poſſeſſes 'em in trembling cold; he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventur'd among Thieves to get them, and now fears by Thieves and Robbers to be depriv'd of 'em again; he labour'd to dig them out of the Earth; and now to ſecure them, he hides them therein. In ſhort, coming from all his Voyages, he comes into a Priſon: and the end of bis bodily travels, is but the beginning of the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs labour of his Mind. Judge now what this Man has gain'd, after ſo many Miſeries. This Devil of Covetouſneſs perſwades him he has ſome rare and excellent thing; and ſo it fares with him as with thoſe poor Creatures whom the Devil ſeduceth under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of relieving their Poverty; who find their hands full of Leaves, when they thought to find them full of Crowns: He poſſeſſeth, or rather is poſſeſſed by, a thing wherein is neither Power nor Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, more baſe and unprofitable than the leaſt Herb of the Earth. Yet hath he heaped together this vile Excrement, and ſo bruitiſh is grown, as therewith to crown his head, when he ought to tread it under his feet.</p>
            <p>But however it be, is he therewith ſatisfied and contented? So far from that, that he is now more diſſatisfied than ever. We com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend moſt thoſe Drinks that breed an alteration, and ſooneſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh Thirſt; and thoſe Meats that in leaſt quantity do longeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt Hunger: But now of this, the more a Man drinks, the more he is athirſt; the more he eats, the more he is an hungry: It is a Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that ſwells him till he burſts, before he can be ſatisfied. And which is worſe, in ſome ſo extravagant is this thirſt, that it makes them dig the pits, and carefully draw the Water, and after all, won't ſuffer 'em to drink: In the midſt of a River, they are dry with thirſt; and on a heap of Corn, cry out of Famine: They have Goods, and dare not uſe them; Garments, but dare not put 'em on: And tho' they are poſſeſs'd of that in which they joy, they don't enjoy it: The ſum of all which is, That of all which they have, they have nothing.</p>
            <p>Let us then return unto that, That the attaining of all theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiveable Goods, is nothing elſe but wearineſs of Body, and the poſſeſſion for the moſt part wearineſs of Mind; which certainly is ſo much the greater Evil, as the Mind is more ſenſible than the Body.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105818:7"/>
            <p>But the Compliment of all their Miſery is, when they come to loſe them, either by ſhipwrack, Fire, or any other Accident, then they cry, weep, and torment themſelves; like little Children, that have loſt their Play-game, which yet is nothing worth. One cannot perſwade them that mortal Men have any other Good in this World, but that which is mortal. They are in their own conceits not only ſpoiled, but utterly undone: And foraſmuch as in theſe vain things they have fix'd all their hope, having loſt them, they fall into Deſpair, out of which they are ſeldom recovered, many times laying violent hands upon themſelves, and bringing their own lives to an unhappy period.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, The recompence that Covetouſneſs yields thoſe that have ſerv'd it all their Life, is like that of the Devil, who after a ſmall time having gratified his Votaries, either leaves them to the Hangman, or himſelf breaks their Necks.</p>
            <p>I will not here diſcourſe of the Wickedneſs to which covetous men ſubject themſelves to attain to theſe Goods, whereby their Conſcience is fill'd with a perpetual Remorſe, which never leaves them in quiet. It is enough that in this immoderate purſuit of Riches, which buſieth and abuſeth the greateſt part of the World, the Body is macerated, the Mind debilitated, and the Soul is loſt, without any Pleaſure or Contentment.</p>
            <p>Let us then come to <hi>Ambition,</hi> which by an over-eager aſpiring to Honour, takes up the time and thoughts of the Greateſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: And what, Do we there think to find more <hi>Content?</hi> Alas! 'Tis rather leſs; and this, I am ſure, I can witneſs to my coſt: For as the one deceives us, by giving us for all our travel but a vile Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement of the Earth; ſo the other repays us but with Smoak and Wind: The Rewards of this, being as vain; as thoſe of that, were groſs. In both we fall into a bottomleſs Pit; but into this, the fall is by ſo much the more dangerous, as at the firſt ſhew the Water is more clear and pleaſant.</p>
            <p>Of thoſe Men that make their court to <hi>Ambition,</hi> ſome are great about Princes, others Commanders of Armies; both ſorts according to their degree, you ſee ſaluted, reverenced, and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of thoſe that are under them: You ſee them apparelled in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in Scarlet, and in Cloth of Gold; that at firſt ſight one would think there is no <hi>Content</hi> to be found but amongſt them. But alas!
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105818:7"/>men know not how heavy an ounce of that vain Honour weighs; they know not what thoſe Reverences coſt them, nor how dearly they pay for an Ell of thoſe rich Stuffs: They are ſo over-rated, that he who knew them well, would never buy them at the Price. The one hath attain'd to this degree, after a long and painful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, hazarding his Life upon every occaſion, with loſs oft-times of a Leg or an Arm; and that at the pleaſure of a Prince that more regards a hundred Perches of Ground on his Neighbours Frontiers, than the Lives of a hundred thouſand ſuch as he; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate to ſerve who loves him not; and fooliſh to think himſelf in honour with him, that makes ſo little reckoning to loſe him for a thing of no worth.</p>
            <p>Others there are that aſpire to Greatneſs by flattering a Prince; which is a Life ſo baſe and ſervile, that they can never ſay their very Souls are their own, any longer than their Prince is pleas'd to let 'em; for they muſt always have their Hands and Tongues ready to do and ſay whatever he would have them; and yet they muſt be content to ſuffer a thouſand Injuries, and receive a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand diſgraces: And as near as they ſeem about the Prince, they are nevertheleſs always like the Lions Keeper, who when by long patience, a thouſand Feedings, and a thouſand Clawings, he hath made a fierce Lion familiar, yet never gives him Meat, but with pulling back his hand, always in fear leaſt he ſhould catch him; and if once in a year he bites him, he ſets it ſo cloſe, that he is paid for a long time after. Such generally is the end of the Favourites of Princes.</p>
            <p>When a Prince after long Service hath rais'd a Man to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pitch of Honour, he ſometimes makes it his Paſtime to caſt him down in an inſtant; and when he hath fill'd him with heaps of Wealth and Riches, he ſqueezes him afterward like a Spunge; loving none but himſelf, and thinking every one born but to ſerve and pleaſe him.</p>
            <p>Theſe blind Courtiers make themſelves believe that they have Friends, and many that honour them; never conſidering that as they make only a ſhew to love and honour every body, ſo others do to them: Their Superiours diſdain them, and never but with ſome kind of ſcorn ſo much as ſalute them. Their Inferiours ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute them, becauſe they have need of them, (I mean of their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105818:8"/>their Food, their Apparel, not their Perſons.) And for their Equals, between whom Friendſhip uſually conſiſts, they envy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, and croſs each other; being always troubled either at their own harm, or at anothers good. Now what greater torment is there to a Man than Envy? Which is indeed nothing but a <hi>Hectick Fever</hi> of the Mind; by which they are utterly depriv'd of all Friendſhip, which was ever judg'd by the Wiſeſt, the Soveraign Good amongſt Men.</p>
            <p>But to make this more evident, Let but Fortune turn her back, and every Man turns from them; let 'em be but diſrob'd of their Triumphal Garment, and no body will know 'em any more. And then ſuppoſe the moſt infamous and vileſt Miſcreant to be cloathed in it, he ſhall by vertue of his Robe, inherit all the Honours of the other, and the ſame Reſpect ſhall be paid him; ſo that it is the Fortune which they carry that is honoured, and not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, At leaſt ſo long as that Fortune endur'd, they were at Eaſe, and had <hi>Content;</hi> and he who has three or four years of Happy Time, has not been all his Life Unhappy. True, if it be to be at Eaſe, continually to fear to be caſt down from that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree unto which they are raiſed; and daily covet with great La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to climb higher. But thoſe whom thou look'ſt upon to be ſo much at eaſe, becauſe thou ſeeſt 'em but without, are within far otherwiſe; they are fair-built Priſons, but full within of deep Dungeons, Darkneſs, Serpents and Torments: Thou ſuppoſeſt their Fortunes very large, but they think them very ſtrait; thou thinkeſt them very high, but they think themſelves very low. Now he is full as ſick, who belleves himſelf to be ſo, as he who indeed is ſo: Suppoſe them to be Kings, yet if they think themſelves Slaves, they are no better; for we are only what Opinion makes us. You ſee them well followed and attended, and yet even thoſe whom they have choſe for their Guard, they diſtruſt. Alone or in company, they are ever in fear: Alone, they look behind them; in company, they have an Eye on every ſide: They drink in Gold and Silver; but 'tis in thoſe, and not in Earth or Glaſs, that Poyſon is prepared: They have Beds ſoft and well made; yet when they lie down to ſleep, their fears and cares do often keep them waking, and turning from ſide to ſide, ſo that their very Reſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105818:8"/>is reſtleſs. And there's no other difference between them and a poor fetter'd Priſoner, but only that the Priſoners Fetters are of Iron, and the others are of Gold; the one is fetter'd by the Body, the other by the Mind; the Priſoner draws his Fetters after him, the Courtier weareth his upon him: The Priſoners Mind ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times comforts the pain of his Body, and he ſings in the midſt of his Miſeries; the Courtier is always troubled in Mind, wearying his Body, and can never give it reſt. And as for the <hi>Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> you imagine they have, you are therein more deceived: You eſteem them Great, becauſe they are raiſed High; but are therein as much miſtaken, as they who ſhould judge a Dwarf to be Tall, for being ſet on a Tower, or ſtanding on the top of the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. You meaſure (like one unskill'd in Geometry) the Image with his Baſe, which you ſhould meaſure by it ſelf, if you would know its true height. You imagine them to be Great, but could you look into their Minds, you would ſee they are neither Great, (true Greatneſs conſiſting in the contempt of thoſe vain Greatneſſes unto which they are Slaves) nor ſeem unto themſelves to be ſo; ſeeing they daily are aſpiring higher, and yet never where they would be.</p>
            <p>Some there are, that pretend to ſet bounds to their Ambition; and to ſay, If I could attain to ſuch a degree, I ſhould be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſit down ſatisfied; but alas! when they have once attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, they ſcarce allow themſelves a breathing time, before they make advances towards ſomething higher; and all he has attain'd he eſteems as nothing, and ſtill reputes himſelf low, becauſe there is ſome one higher; inſtead of reputing himſelf high, becauſe there are a million lower: And ſo high he climbs at laſt, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his breath fails him by the way, or he ſlides from the top to the bottom.</p>
            <p>But if he ſhould get up, by all his toil and labour, unto the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt height of his deſires, he would but find himſelf as on the top of the <hi>Alps,</hi> not above the Clouds, but more obnoxious to the Winds and Storms; and ſo a fairer Mark for thoſe Lightnings and Tempeſts which commonly take pleaſure to Thunderbolt and daſh to powder that proud height of theirs.</p>
            <p>It may be herein you will agree with me, compell'd thereto by thoſe many Examples that we find in the Hiſtories of former Ages,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105818:9"/>and thoſe more Modern ones that are ſtill recent in moſt Mens Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories: But my own ſad Experience is, to me, more convincing than a thouſand Inſtances; while aiming at a higher pitch of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, by a too forward Zeal for my Prince, I have only brought my ſelf into a Priſon; where the greateſt Preferment I can hope for, is to mount a Scaffold; and inſtead of having my head circled with a Coronet, 'tis like to fall a Victim to my Enemies, by the hands of an Executioner.</p>
            <p>But ſay you, Such at leaſt whom Nature hath ſent into the World with Crowns on their Heads, and Scepters in their Hands; ſuch as from their Birth are plac'd in that high Sphere, that they have nothing more to wiſh for; ſuch are exempt from all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd Evils, and therefore may call themſelves happy: It may be indeed they may be leſs ſenſible of them, having been born, bred, and brought up amongſt them: As one born near the down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls of <hi>Nilus,</hi> becomes deaf to the ſound of thoſe Waters; and he that is born and brought up in Priſon, laments not the loſs of Liberty; nor does he wiſh for Day, that is brought up amongſt the <hi>Cimmerians</hi> in perpetual Night. Yet even Perſons of this high Quality, are far from being free; for the Lightening often blaſts a Flower of their Crowns, or breaks the Scepter in their hands; ſometimes their Crowns are made of Thorns, and the Scepter that they bear is but a Reed: And ſuch Crowns and Scepters are ſo far from curing the Chagrin of the Mind, and from keeping off thoſe Cares and Griefs that hover ſtill about 'em, that on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, it is the Crown that brings them, and the Scepter that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts them. <hi>O Crown,</hi> ſaid the Perſian Monarch, <hi>He that knew how heavy thou ſitteſt on the Head, would not vouchſafe to take thee up, tho' he ſhould meet thee in his way.</hi> This Prince gave Law to the whole World, and each Mans Fortune, was what he pleas'd to make it; and therefore to appearance could give to every Man <hi>Content;</hi> and yet you ſee himſelf confeſſing, That in the whole World, which he held in his hand, there was nothing but Grief and Unhappineſs.</p>
            <p>And what better account can the reſt give us, if they will ſpeak impartially what they found? We will not ask them who have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded a miſerable Life with a Diſhonourable Death; who have beheld their Kingdoms buried before them, and have in great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105818:9"/>long over-liv'd their Greatneſs. Neither will we enquire of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant of <hi>Sicily,</hi> who was more content with a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Twigs to whip the little Children of <hi>Corinth</hi> in a School, than with the Scepter wherewith he had beaten all <hi>Sicily:</hi> Nor will we ask of <hi>Sylla,</hi> who having robb'd the Commonwealth of <hi>Rome,</hi> which had her ſelf before robb'd the whole World, never found means of reſt in himſelf, but by robbing himſelf of his own Eſtate, with incredible hazzard of his Power and Authority. Nor (to come nearer home) will we enquire of <hi>Charles</hi> the Royal Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, the luſtre of whoſe Crown did only ſerve to tempt his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, not only to take it from his Head, but to take his Head off too; and whoſe Scepter was too weak to overcome the force of Armed Rebells. Nor will we ask of his two Exil'd Sons, the firſt of which endur'd Twelve years of Baniſhment ere he enjoy'd his Crown; and the laſt, in leſs than a <hi>Quinque Neronem,</hi> was forc'd to leave his Crown and Kingdoms, and fly for Refuge to a Neighbouring Monarch, whoſe Generous Goodneſs has ever ſince ſupported him; whoſe ſad Misfortunes I the more regret, becauſe they both include my own, and are their Source and Fountain. It is of none of theſe unhappy Princes that we will make Enquiry after Happineſs: But let us ask the Opinion of the moſt Opulent and flouriſhing of Princes, even of the great Kings <hi>Solomon,</hi> a Man endew'd with ſingular Wiſdom from Above, beyond the reſt of Men; and whoſe immenſe Riches was ſo great, that Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were as plentiful as the Stones in the Street; and the Sacred Hiſtory tells us, There was ſuch plenty of Gold, that Silver was nothing accounted of, in the days of <hi>Solomon;</hi> and as he wanted not Treaſure, ſo neither did he want for largeneſs of heart to make uſe of it: And after he had try'd all the Felicities that the World could afford him, this is the account that he gives of it, <hi>All is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and vexation of Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we ask of the Emperor <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> who peaceably poſſeſs'd the whole world, He will bewail his Life paſt, and among infinite Toils, wiſh for the Reſt of the meaneſt of his Subjects; eſteeming that a happy Day that would eaſe him of his inſupportable Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſuffer him to live quietly among the leaſt.</p>
            <p>If of <hi>Tiberius</hi> his Succeſſor, he will tell us, <hi>That he holds the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, as a Wolf by the Ears, and that (if he could do it without danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105818:10"/>bitten, he would gladly let it go;</hi> complaining on Fortune for lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſo high, and then taking away the Ladder, that he could not get down.</p>
            <p>If of <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> a Prince of great Wiſdom and Vertue in the Opinion of the World; he will prefer his voluntary Baniſhment at <hi>Solona;</hi> before all the Roman Empire.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, If of the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, eſteemed the moſt happy that hath liv'd theſe many Ages, He will curſe his Conqueſts, Victories and Triumphs; and not be aſhamed to own, That he hath felt more Good in one day of his Monkiſh Solitude, than in all his Triumphant Life.</p>
            <p>Now can we imagine thoſe happy in this imaginary Greatneſs, who think themſelves unhappy in it? And do profeſs that Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs conſiſts in being leſſer and not greater. In a word, What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Happineſs <hi>Ambition</hi> promiſeth, it is nothing elſe, but ſuffering of much Evil, to get more. Men think by daily climbing higher, to pluck themſelves out of this Evil; and yet the height whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they ſo painfully aſpire, is the height of miſery it ſelf.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not here of the wretchedneſs of them, who all their Lives have been holding out their Caps to Fortune for the Alms of Court-Favour, and can get nothing; nor of them who joſtling one another for it, caſt it into the hands of a third; nor of thoſe who having it, and ſeeking to hold it faſter, drop it through their Fingers, which often happens. Such by all Men are eſteem'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy; and are ſo indeed, becauſe they judge themſelves ſo.</p>
            <p>Well, you will now ſay, The <hi>Covetous</hi> in all his Goods, hath no Good; the <hi>Ambitious</hi> at the beſt he can be, is but ill: But may there not be ſome, who ſupplying the place of Juſtice, or being near about a Prince, may without following ſuch unbridled Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, enjoy their Goods with Innocence and Pleaſure, joyning Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour with Reſt, and Contentment of Mind?</p>
            <p>Perhaps in former Ages (when there remain'd among Men ſome ſparks of Sincerity) it might in ſome ſort be ſo; but being of that compoſition they now are, it is in a manner, impoſſible: For if you deal in Affairs of State, you ſhall either do well or ill; if ill, you have God for your Enemy, and your own Conſcience for a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually tormenting Executioner: If well, you have Men for your Enemies, and of Men the Greateſt; whoſe Envy and Malice will
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105818:10"/>ſpy you out, and whoſe Cruelty and Tyranny will evermore threaten you. Pleaſe the People, you pleaſe a Beaſt; and pleaſing ſuch, ought to be diſpleaſing to your ſelf. Pleaſe your ſelf, you diſpleaſe God: pleaſe Him, you incur a thouſand dangers in the World, with the purchaſe of a thouſand diſpleaſures. The ſum of all therefore is this, There are none contented with their preſent ſtations; for if you could hear the talk of the wiſeſt and leaſt diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented of Men, whether they ſpeak adviſedly, or their words paſs them by force of truth, One would gladly change Garments with his Tenant: Another preacheth how goodly an eſtate it is to have nothing: A third, complaining that his brains are broken with the noiſe of Court or Palace, hath no other thought, but as ſoon as he can to retire himſelf thence. So that you ſhall not ſee any but is diſpleaſed with his own calling, and envieth that of another: And yet ready to recoil, if a Man ſhould take him at his word. None but is weary of the Inconveniencies whereunto his Age is ſubject, and yet wiſhes not to be elder, to free himſelf of them, tho' other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he keeps off old Age as much as in him lyeth.</p>
            <p>What muſt we then do in ſo great a contrariety and confuſion of minds? Muſt we, to find true Contentment, fly the ſociety of Men, hide us in Forreſts among wild Beaſts, and ſequeſter our ſelves from all converſation, to preſerve our ſelves from the evil of the World? Could we in ſo doing live at reſt, it were ſomething; But alas! Men cannot take herein what part they would; and even they which do, find not there all the Reſt they ſought for.</p>
            <p>But where can he fly, that carries his Enemy in his Boſom? And ſince, as the wiſe Man ſays, The World is in our Hearts, hardly can we find a place in this World, where the World will not find us. And as ſome make profeſſion to fly the World, who thereby ſeek nothing but the praiſe of the World; and as ſome hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from Men, to no other end but that Men ſhould ſeek them; ſo the World often harbors in diſguiſed Attire, among them that fly the World. It is not therefore Solitude and Retirement can give us Contentment, but only the ſubduing of our unruly Luſts and Paſſions.</p>
            <p>Now as touching that Contentment that may be found in Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude by wiſe Men, in the Exerciſe of Reading divers Books, of both Divine and Prophane Authors, in order to the acquiring of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105818:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Learning, it is indeed a very commendable thing; but if we will take <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Judgment in the Caſe, it is all but vanity and vexation of Spirit: For ſome are ever learning to correct their Speech, and never think of correcting their Life. Others by Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Diſcourſes of the Art of Reaſon, diſpute many times ſo long, till they loſe thereby their Natural Reaſon. One learns by Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick to divide into the ſmalleſt Fractions, and yet hath not skill to part one Shilling with his Brother. Another by Geometry can meaſure Fields, and Towns, and Countries: But cannot meaſure himſelf. The Muſitian can accord his Voices, and Sounds, and Times together; Having nothing in his Heart but Diſcords; nor one Paſſion in his Soul, but what is out of tune. The Aſtrologer looks up to the Stars, and falls in the next Ditch: Fore-knows the future, and is careleſs for the preſent; hath often his Eye on the Heavens, tho' his Heart be buried in the Earth. The Philoſopher diſcourſeth of the nature of all other things; and yet knows not himſelf. The Hiſtorian can tell of the Wars of <hi>Thebes</hi> and of <hi>Troy;</hi> but is ignorant of what is done in his own Houſe. The Lawyer will make Laws for all the World, and yet obſerve none himſelf. The Phyſitian Cures others, but languiſhes himſelf under his own Malady: He can find the leaſt alteration in his Pulſe, but takes no notice of the burning Feaver of his Mind. Laſtly, the Divine will ſpend the greateſt part of his time in diſputing of Faith, and yet cares not to hear of Charity: Will talk of god, but has no regard to ſuccour Men. Theſe knowledges bring on the Mind an endleſs labour, but no contentment; for the more he knows, the more he deſires to know.</p>
            <p>They pacifie not the Debates a Man feels in himſelf, they cure not the diſeaſes of his Mind. They make him learned, but they make him not good; cunning, but not wiſe. The more a Man knows, the more he knows that he knows not; the fuller the Mind is, the emptier it finds it ſelf: Foraſmuch as whatſoever a Man can know of any Science in this world, is but the leaſt part of what he is ignorant of: All his knowledge conſiſting in knowing his ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nroance, all his perfection in ſeeing his imperfections, which who beſt knows and notes, is in truth among Men the moſt wiſe and perfect. In ſhort we muſt conclude with <hi>Solomon,</hi> that the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and end of Wiſdom is the fear of God; yet this Wiſdom
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105818:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>nevertheleſs is taken by the World for meer Folly, and perſecuted by the World as a deadly Enemy; and therefore, as he that fears God, ought to fear no evil, for that all his evils are converted to his good: So neither ought he to hope for good in the World, having there the Devil his profeſſed Enemy, whom the Scripture termeth Prince of this World.</p>
            <p>But with what exerciſe ſoever we paſs the time, old Age una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares comes upon us, which never failes to find us out. Every Man makes account in that Age to repoſe himſelf without further care, and to keep himſelf at eaſe in health. But on the contrary, in this age, there is nothing but an after-taſt of all the foregoing evils; and moſt commonly a plentiful harveſt of all ſuch Vices as in the whole courſe of their Life, hath held and poſſeſſed them. There you have the Imbecility and Weakneſs of Infancy, and (which is worſe) many times accompanied with authority: There you are paid for the exceſs and riot of your Youth, with Gouts, Palſies, and ſuch like Diſeaſes, which take from you Limb after Limb, with pain and torment. There you are recompenc'd for the anxieties of Mind, the watchings and cares of Manhood, with Ioſs of Sight, loſs of Hearing, and all the Sences one after another, except only the ſence of Pain. Not one part in us but Death takes hold of, to be aſſured of us, as of bad pay-maſters, which ſeldom keep days of payment; There is nothing in us which is not viſible declining, except our Vices; and they not only live, but in deſpite of Nature, grow young again. The Covetous Man hath one Foot in his Grave, and is yet burying his Money, as if he had hopes to find it again another day. The Ambitious in his Will provides for a pompous Funeral, making his vice to triumph even after his Death. The Riotous no longer able to dance on his Feet, danceth with his Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, all Vices having left him, and he not able to leave them. The Child wiſhes for Youth; and this Man laments it. The Young Man lives in hope of the future, and this feels the evil preſent, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the falſe pleaſures paſt, and ſees for the time to come nothing to hope for. And is more fooliſh than the Child, in bewailing the time he cann't recall, and remembers not the evil that he ſuffer'd in it; and more wretched than the Young Man, in that after a vicious life, and not being able any longer to live, he muſt miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably die, ſeeing nothing round about him but matter of deſpair.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:105818:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>As for him that from his Youth hath undertaken to combat againſt the fleſh and the World, who hath uſed to mortifie himſelf, and leave the World whilſt he continues in it; who beſides thoſe ordinary Evils, finds himſelf vexed with this great and incurable Diſeaſe of Old Age; and yet feels his Fleſh, how weak ſoever, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtronger than his Spirit; what ſatisfaction can he take, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this, that he ſees his death is at hand; that his Warfare is accompliſhed, and that he is ready to depart by Death out of this loathſome Priſon, wherein he has been all along rack'd and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented?</p>
            <p>I forbear to mention the almoſt infinite Evils wherewith Men in all Ages are afflicted, as loſs of Friends and Parents, Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Exiles, Diſgraces, and other Accidents, common and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary in the World; one complaining of loſing his Children, another of having them; one lamenting for his Wives Death, another for her Life; one finding fault that he is too high in Court, and others more often that they are not high enough. The World is ſo full of Evils, that it would require a World of Time to write 'em in. And if the moſt happy Man in the World ſhould ſet his Felicities and Infelicities againſt each other, he would ſee cauſe enough to judge himſelf unhappy: And yet perhaps another Man might judge him happy, who yet if he had been but three days in his place, would give it over to him that ſhould come next. And he that ſhall conſider, in all the Goods that ever he hath had, the Evils he hath ſuffered to get them, and having got them, to retain and keep them, (I ſpeak of Pleaſures that may be kept, and not of thoſe that wither in a moment) he will ſoon judge that keeping it ſelf of the greateſt Felicity in this World, is full of Unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Infelicity.</p>
            <p>We may well conclude then, That Childhood is but a fooliſh Simplicity; Youth, a vain Heat; Manhood, a painful Carefulneſs; and Old Age, an uneaſie Languiſhing: That our Plays are but Tears, our Pleaſures, Fevers of the Mind; our Goods, Racks and Torments; our Honours, gilded Vanities; our Reſt, Inquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: That paſſing from Age to Age, is but paſſing from Evil to Evil, and from the leſs unto the greater; and that always it is but one Wave driving on another, until we be arrived at the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Death.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105818:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>In ſhort, Life is but a wiſhing for the future, and a bewailing of what's paſt; a loathing of what we have taſted, and a longing for what is yet to taſte; a vain memory of the ſtate paſt, and a doubtful expectation of the ſtate to come: And to conclude, In all our Life there is nothing certain, but the Certainty and Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Death.</p>
            <p>And now we are come to the end of all the Living, even to the Houſe of Death: Behold this King of Terrors, O my Soul, and ſee whether or no he be ſo terrible as he is repreſented: It is high time, methinks, for Death and I to be acquainted, ſince I expect in a very few days (not to ſay hours) to be taken into his Arms, and conducted by him to the bright Manſions of Eternity.</p>
            <p>Let us now conſider then whether Death be ſuch as we are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally made to believe; and whether we ought to fly from him as we do: We are afraid of Death like little Children of a Vizzard, or of the Images of <hi>Hecate:</hi> We have a horror for Death, becauſe we conceive him not ſuch as he is, but ugly, terrible, and hideous; ſuch as the Painters pleaſe to repreſent him: We fly before him becauſe prepoſſeſs'd with ſuch vain Imaginations, and care not to inform our ſelves better. But if we dare ſtand and look Death in the face, we ſhall find him quite another thing than he is repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us, and altogether of a more amiable Countenance than our miſerable Life. Death makes an end of this Life, and this Life is nothing but a perpetual Scene of Miſery and Trouble; Death then is the period of our Miſeries, and ſafe Conduct into that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Haven, where we ſhall ride in ſafety from all Winds and Storms: And ſhall we be afraid of that which delivers us from all our fears, and brings us ſafe into the Port of Happineſs?</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, It is a Pain to dye: Admit it be, and ſo there's pain in curing of a Wound: Such is the World, that one Evil cann't be cur'd but by another; to heal a Contuſion, muſt be made an Inciſion.</p>
            <p>You will ſay, There is difficulty in the paſſage: But if this be an Objection, the Mariner muſt always keep at Sea, and not come into Port, becauſe there is no Harbour whoſe Entrance is not ſtrait and difficult. There is nothing of Value or Worth to be had in this World without the Coyn of Labour and Pain. The Entrance may indeed be hard, but then it is our ſelves that make
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105818:13"/>it ſo, by carrying thither ſelf-tormenting Spirits, anxious Minds, accuſing Conſciences, and fearful expectations of meeting with the juſt Reward of a Debauch'd and Vicious Life: But let us car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with us Calmneſs and Serenity of Mind, with the comfortable remembrance of a Vertuous and well-ſpent Life, and the lively hope and expectation of approaching Happineſs, and we ſhall find no Danger nor Difficulty at all.</p>
            <p>But what are the pains that Death brings us? And why ſhould Death be charg'd with thoſe pains we feel when we come to dye? We accuſe Death of all the Evils we ſuffer in ending our Lives, and conſider not how many more grievous and cruciating Pains and Sickneſſes we have ſuffered in this Life, in which we have even call'd upon Death to deliver us; and yet all the Pains of our Life, to our laſt moment, we impute to Death, whereas it ought to be aſcrib'd to Life; for 'tis but reaſonable to believe that a Life begun and continued in all ſorts of pain, muſt of neceſſity end ſo: And therefore 'tis only the remainder of our Life that pains us, and not Death; the end of our Navigation that troubles us, and not the Haven that we are to enter, which is nothing elſe but a Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard againſt all Winds. We complain of Death, when we ſhould complain of Life, juſt as if one that had been long ſick, and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to be well, ſhould accuſe his Health of his laſt Pains, and not the Relicks of his Diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>Tell me then, what is it elſe to be dead, but to be no more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the World? And is it any pain not to be in the World? Did we then feel pain when as yet we were not? Have we ever more reſemblance of Death, than when we are aſleep? Or ever more reſt, than at that time? Now if this be no pain, why ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe we Death of the Pains our Life gives us at our departure? Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs alſo we will fondly accuſe the Time wherein we were not, of the pains we felt at our Birth. If our coming in be with Tears, what wonder is it that our going out be ſuch? If the beginning of our being, be the beginning of our pain, no marvel that ſuch is the ending. But if our not being in times paſt, hath been without pain, and all our being here full of pain; whom ought we in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to accuſe of our laſt pains, the not-being to come, or the remnant of the preſent being?</p>
            <p>We generally think we dye not until we fetch our laſt gaſp, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105818:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>if we mind it well, we ſhall find that we dye every day, every hour, every moment. We apprehend Death as a thing unuſual to us, and yet have nothing ſo common in us: Our Living is but a continual Dying; and look how much we live, ſo much we dye; how much we increaſe, our Life decreaſes: We cannot enter a ſtep into Life, but we are upon the borders of Death. Who has lived a third part of his years, is a third part dead; who half his years, is already half dead. Of our Life, all the time paſt is dead, the preſent lives and dies at once, and the future likewiſe ſhall dye.</p>
            <p>The paſt time of our Lives is no more, the future is not yet, the preſent is, and no more is.</p>
            <p>Briefly, This whole Life is but a Death: It is as a Candle light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our Bodies: In one the Wind makes it melt away, in another it blows it quite out, many times, ere it be half burned; in others it endures to the end: Howſoever it be, look how much the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſhines, ſo much it burns; for its ſhining is its burning: Its Light is but a vaniſhing Smoak; and its laſt Fire but its laſt Wick, and its laſt drop of moiſture.</p>
            <p>So is it in the Life of Man; Life and Death in Man, is all one: If we call the laſt breath by the name of Death, ſo we muſt all the reſt; all proceeding from one place, and all in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>One only difference there is between this Life, and that which we call death; That during the one, we are always dying; but after the other, we ſhall always live.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, As he that thinketh Death ſimply to be the End of Man, ought not to fear it; inaſmuch as he who deſires to live long, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to dye longer; and ſo he who fears to dye quickly, does (to ſpeak properly) fear leaſt he may not dye longer.</p>
            <p>But to us who profeſs the Chriſtian Religion, and are brought up in a more holy School, Death is a far other thing; neither do we need (as heretofore the Pagans did) Conſolations againſt Death: For Death it ſelf ought to be to us a Conſolation againſt other Afflictions: So that we muſt not only ſtrengthen our ſelves (as they did) not to fear it; but we ought alſo to hope it: For unto us it is not only a departing from Pain and Evil, but an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs unto all Good; not the end of Life, but the end of Death,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105818:14"/>and Pain, and Sorrow; and the beginning of a Life that ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have an end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Better</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) is the Day of Death, than the Day of Birth:</hi> But for what Reaſon? Why becauſe it is not to us a <hi>Laſt Day,</hi> but the Dawning of an <hi>Everlaſting Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No more ſhall we have in that glorious Light either Sorrow for the paſt, or Expectation for the future; for all ſhall be there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to us, and that Preſent ſhall be preſent for ever. No more ſhall we ſpend our ſtrength in ſeeking after vain and painful Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; for there we ſhall be fill'd with true and ſubſtantial De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights. No more ſhall we weary our ſelves in heaping together theſe ſhining Exhalations of the Earth; for the inexpreſſible Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Heaven ſhall be ours: And this Maſs of Earth, which ever draws us towards the Earth, ſhall be then buried in it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with it.</p>
            <p>No more ſhall we then be Votaries to that gaudy Idol, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; nor put our Wits upon the Rack, that ſo we may be deck'd with finer Feathers than our Neighbours: Ambition will have there no place; for we ſhall there be rais'd to that Excelling Glory, and be poſſeſs'd of all thoſe Heighths of Greatneſs, that we ſhall look with ſcorn and with contempt upon an Earthly Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem; and ſmile at all the Follies of poor groveling Mortals, who fight and quarrel with each other for a ſmall ſpot of Earth, like Children for an Apple.</p>
            <p>And (which is better ſtill) no more ſhall we have Combats in our ſelves; Our ſinful Fleſh (that here was our worſt Enemy) ſhall ceaſe from troubling there; and our renewed Spirits ſhall be fill'd with Life and Vigour: Our Paſſion ſhall be buried, and our Reaſon be reſtor'd to perfect Liberty: The Soul (deliver'd out of this foul and filthy Priſon, where by its long continuing it is grown into a habit of Crookedneſs) ſhall again draw its own breath, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognize its Ancient Dwelling, and again remember its former Glory and Dignity.</p>
            <p>This Fleſh which thou feeleſt, this Body which thou toucheſt, is not Man: Man is a Spark of the Divinity ſhot down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Heaven is his Countrey, and his Native Air: That he is in this Body, is but by way of Exile and Confinement.</p>
            <p>Man indeed is Soul and Spirit, and is of a Divine and Heavenly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105818:14"/>Quality, wherein there's nothing groſs, nothing material. This Body (ſuch as now it is) is but the Bark and Shell of the Soul; which muſt neceſſarily be broke, before we can be hatch'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can live and ſee the Light.</p>
            <p>We have, it ſeems, ſome Life, and ſome Sence in us; but are ſo very crooked and contracted, that we cannot ſo much as ſtretch out our Wings, much leſs take our flight towards Heaven, until we be disburthen'd and ſeparated from this Lump of Earth: We look, but 'tis through falſe Spectacles: We have Eyes, but they are over-grown with Pearls: We think we ſee, but 'tis but in a Dream, wherein all that we ſee is nothing but a vain Illuſion: All that we ſeem to have, and all that we ſeem to know, is but De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and Vanity.</p>
            <p>Death only can awake us from our Dream, and reſtore us to true Life and Light; and yet we think (ſo blockiſh are we) that he comes to rob us of them.</p>
            <p>We profeſs our ſelves Chriſtians, and that we believe after this mortal Life a Life of Immortality; That Death is nothing but a ſeparation of the Soul and Body; and that the Soul returns to its former happy abode, there to joy in and enjoy the Fountain of all Bliſs; and that at the laſt day it ſhall re-aſſume its Body, which ſhall no more be ſubject to Corruption. With theſe goodly Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cousſes we fill our Books; and in the mean while, when it comes to to the point, and that we are ready to enter in at this Portcullis of Seraphical Glory, the very Name of Death, as of ſome dreadful <hi>Gorgon,</hi> makes us quake and tremble.</p>
            <p>If we believe as we ſpeak, pray what is it that we fear? To be happy? To be perfectly at eaſe? To enjoy more Content in one moment, than ever was enjoy'd even by <hi>Methuſelah</hi> himſelf, in all his Nine hundred ſixty nine years, which was the longeſt mortal Life I ever read of? If this be nothing that we fear, then we muſt of neceſſity confeſs, that we believe it but in part; that all that we have ſaid, are only words; that all our Diſcourſes, as of thoſe hardy Trencher Knights, are nothing but Vaunting and Vanity.</p>
            <p>Some there are that will confidently tell you, I know very well that I ſhall paſs out of this Life into a better; I make no doubt of that; only I fear the mid-way ſtep.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105818:15"/>
            <p>Weak Hearted Creatures! They will kill themſelves to get their miſerable living: They willingly ſuffer almoſt infinite pains, and infinite wounds at another Mans pleaſure; and fearleſs go throw infinite deaths without dying, and all this for things of nought, for things that periſh, and that oft times cauſes them to periſh with them. But when they have but one ſtep to make to be at Reſt, and that not for a day, but for ever: And not barely Reſt, but a Reſt of that exalted Nature, that Mans natural Mind can never comprehend: They tremble, their Hearts fail them, they are afraid; and yet it is nothing but fear that hurts them. Let them never tell me, they apprehend the pain: It is but an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe on purpoſe to conceal the little Faith they have. No, no, they would rather languiſh of the Gout, the Sciatica, or any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe whatſoever, than dye one ſweet Death with the leaſt pain poſſible: Rather piningly dye Limb after Limb, out-living as it were, all their Sences, Motions, and Actions, than ſpeedily Dye, tho' immediatly to Live for ever. Let them tell me no more that they would in this World learn to Live: For every one is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſufficiently inſtructed in himſelf, and not one but is cunning in the Trade. Nay rather they ſhould learn in this World to Dye, and that they may once Dye well, to Dye daily in themſelves; ſo prepared, as if the end of every days Work, were the end of our Life.</p>
            <p>Now contrariwiſe there is nothing to their Ears more offenſive, than to hear of Death. Senſeleſs People! We abandon our Life to the ordinary hazzards of War, for Six Pence a Day, and are foremoſt in Aſſaults, for a little Booty; go into Places, whence there is no hope of returning, with danger many times both of Bodies and Souls. But to free us from all Hazzards, to win the precious Prize of things Ineſtimable, to enter into Eternal Life, we Faint in the paſſage of one Pace, wherein is no Difficulty, but in Opinion: Yea we ſo Faint, that were it not of neceſſity that we muſt paſs, and that Gods ordination that all muſt dye, compells us, hardly ſhould we find in all the World one, how unhappy or wretched ſoever, that would ever ſhoot that Gulph. Another will ſay, had I liv'd till Fifty or Sixty Years, I ſhould have been Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented; I ſhould not have car'd to live longer: But to dye ſo Young, is that which troubles me: I would willingly have known
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105818:15"/>the World before I had left it. Simple Soul! In this World there is neither Young nor Old. The longeſt Age in compariſon of all that is paſt, or all that is to come, is nothing: And when thou haſt liv'd to the Age thou now deſireſt, all that is paſt will be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: Thou wilt ſtill gape for that which is to come. The paſt will yield thee but Sorrow, the future but Expectation, the preſent no Contentment. And thou wilt be as unwilling to Dye then, as ever thou was't. Thou flieſt thy Creditor from Mouth to Month, and Time to Time, as unwilling to pay the laſt day, as the firſt: Thou ſeekeſt but to be acquitted. Thou haſt taſted all which the World eſteemeth Pleaſures: Not one of them is new unto thee. By drinking oftener, thou ſhalt be never a whit the more ſatisfied: For the Body thou carrieſt, like the Paile of <hi>Danaus</hi> Daughter, which was bored full of holes, will never be full. Thou mayſt ſooner wear it out, than weary thy ſelf with uſing, or rather abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it. Thou deſireſt long Life, to caſt it away, to ſpend it on worthleſs Delights, to miſ-ſpend it on Vanities. Thou art Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous in deſiring, and Prodigal in ſpending. Say not thou findeſt fault with the Court, or the Palace: But that thou deſireſt longer to ſerve the Common-Wealth, to ſerve thy Country, to ſerve God. He that ſet thee on Work knows until what Day, and what Hour, thou ſhouldeſt be at it: He well knows how to direct his Work. Should he leave thee there longer, perhaps thou wouldeſt ſpoil all. But if he will pay thee liberally for thy Labour, as much for half a days Work, as for a whole: As much for having wrought till noon, as for having born all the heat of the day: Oughteſt thou not ſo much the more to Thank and Praiſe him? But if thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin thine own Conſcience, thou lamenteſt not the cauſe of the Widow, and the Orphan, which thou haſt left depending in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Not the Duty of a Son, of a father, or of a Friend, which thou pretendeſt thou wouldeſt perform: Not the Ambaſſage for the Common-Wealth, which thou wert ever ready to undertake: Not the Service thou deſireſt to do unto God, who knows much better how to ſerve himſelf of thee, than thou of thy ſelf. It is thy Houſes and Gardens thou lamenteſt, thy imperfect Plots and purpoſes, and thy Imperfect Life; which yet no Days, nor Years, nor Ages can make Perfect, altho' thy ſelf might'ſt do it in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; could'ſt thou but think in earneſt, that where, or when it ends, it matters not, provided that it ends but well.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:105818:16"/>
            <p>Now the only way to end this Life well, is to end it willingly: devoting our ſelves with an intire Reſignation to the will of GOD, and not ſuffering our ſelves to be conſtrain'd, and drawn by the force of unavoidable Deſtiny,</p>
            <p>And then toend this Life willingly, We muſt hope for Death, not fear it.</p>
            <p>To hope for Death, we muſt certainly look, after this Life, for a better.</p>
            <p>To look for a better Life, we muſt fear GOD: And he that truly fears GOD, has nothing elſe he ought to fear in this World, and has reaſon to hope for all things in the World to come.</p>
            <p>To one well reſolved in theſe Points, Death muſt needs be ſweet and agreeable: Knowing that through it he is to enter into the fulneſs of Joy.</p>
            <p>The Bitterneſs we may find by the ſtraitneſs of the Paſſage, will be allay'd by the Sweetneſs we ſhall find when we are enter'd in: Our ſuffering of Ill, ſhall be ſwallow'd up in the enjoyment of Good: And the Sting of Death it ſelf (which is nothing but Fear) ſhall be dead.</p>
            <p>Nay. I will ſay more, He ſhall not only triumph over all thoſe Evils ſuppoſed to be in Death, but he ſhall alſo ſcorn all thoſe Evils Men fear to meet with in this Life, and look upon 'em as unconcern'd.</p>
            <p>For what can he fear, whoſe Death is his hope? If you think to baniſh him his Country, he knows he has a Country from whence you cannot baniſh him; and that all theſe Countries are but Inns, from which he muſt part in a little time. If to put him in a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he can have none more ſtrait than his own Body: nor none more filthy or dark, or more repleat of Racks and Torments: Or if you think to kill him, you only then compleat his hopes, for Death's what he deſires. And for the manner of it, Be it by Fire, by Sword, by Halter, or by Ax; within three years, within three days, within three hours, it is all one to him; he matters not the time, nor minds the way, by which he paſſes from this miſerable Life: For his Work is ended, his Affairs diſpatch'd; and by the ſelf-ſame way that he goes out, he hopes to enter into a moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and everlaſting Life. Men can but threaten with Death, and Death is all he promiſeth himſelf: The worſt that they do, is but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105818:16"/>to make him dye, and Death is the beſt thing (in his account) that he can hope for.</p>
            <p>The Threatnings of a Tyrant, to him are Promiſes; the Swords of his greateſt Enemies againſt him, he reckons drawn in his ſavour; foraſmuch as he knows, That threatening him Death, they threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en him Life; and the moſt Mortal Wounds can make him but Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal.</p>
            <p>The ſum of all is, He that fears <hi>GOD,</hi> fears not <hi>Death;</hi> and he that fears not <hi>Death,</hi> fears not the worſt of this Life.</p>
            <p>By this reckoning (perhaps ſome Men may ſay) <hi>Death</hi> is a thing to be wiſhed for: And to paſs from ſo much Evil, to ſo much Good, a Man would be ready to caſt away his Life, and make away himſelf.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to this, we may take notice, Firſt, That tho' the Spirit aſpires towards Heaven, the Body draws towards the Earth, and the Soul is too often drawn by the Body. But in the ſecond place; We muſt indeed ſeek to mortifie our Fleſh in us, and to caſt the World out of us; but to caſt our ſelves out of this World, is in no caſe lawful.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian ought willingly to depart out of this Life, but not cowardly to run away. His Work is to fight againſt the World, and cannot leave his poſt, without Reproach and Infamy. But if his Great Captain be pleas'd to call him, let him willingly obey: For he is not born for himſelf, but for <hi>GOD,</hi> of whom he holds his Life at farm, as Tenant at will, to yield him the profits. It is in the Landlord to take it from him, not in him to ſurrender it, when a conceit takes him.</p>
            <p>Dieſt thou young? Praiſe <hi>GOD;</hi> as the Mariner that hath a good Wind, ſoon to bring him to the Port.</p>
            <p>Dieſt thou old? Praiſe <hi>GOD</hi> likewiſe: For if thou haſt had leſs Wind, it may be thou haſt alſo had leſs Waves.</p>
            <p>But think not at thy pleaſure to go faſter or ſlower, for the Wind is not in thy Power; and inſtead of taking the ſhorteſt way to the Haven, thou may'ſt ſuffer ſhipwrack.</p>
            <p>Let us then neither fly from <hi>Death,</hi> when we are call'd to dye, whether it be in a more natural way, as by Old Age, or Sickneſs; or by a more violent way, as by the Sword in Battel, or by the hand of an Executioner; Nor fly to it, not being call'd: Which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105818:17"/>both argues the greateſt Baſeneſs and Puſilanimity of Spirit, and will alſo bring the guilt of our own Blood upon our own Heads: But let us meet <hi>Death,</hi> whenever or however it comes, with that Magnanimity and Greatneſs of Mind, that becomes both a Man and a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>And now having beguil'd my Solitary Hours in Contemplating the Miſeries of Life, and Happineſs of <hi>Death,</hi> to me ſo much the more neceſſary, by how much it is nearer approaching; I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with a Valediction to the World, and all its vain Delights, written by a very Great Man, and Prime Miniſter of State, in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, whilſt under my unhappy Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and but a little before his Execution.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>GO, Empty Joys, with all your Noiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And leave me here alone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In ſad ſweet Silence to bemoan</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>your vain and fond Delight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whoſe Dangers none can ſee aright,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whilſt too much Sunſhine blinds his ſight:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Go and enſnare with your falſe Ware,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some other eaſie Wight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And cheat him with your flattering Light:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rain on his head a Show'r, of Honour, Greatneſs, Wealth and Pow'r,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then ſnatch it from him in an Hour:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fill his big Mind with the vain Wind of flattering Applauſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let him not fear all Curbing Laws,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor King nor People's Frown;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But dream of ſomething like a Crown,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Climbing tow'rds it, Tumble down.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105818:17"/>
            <head>A TRUE COPY OF THE PAPER Delivered to the Sheriffs upon the Scaffold at <hi>Tower-Hill,</hi> on <hi>Thurſday, January</hi> the 28th 1696/7.</head>
            <p>By Sir <hi>JOHN FENWICK,</hi> Baronet.</p>
            <p>SPeaking nor Writing was never my Talent; I ſhall therefore give a very Short but Faithful Account, firſt, of my Religion; and next, what I ſuffer moſt innocently for, to avoid the Calumnies I may reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably expect my Enemies will caſt upon me when dead, ſince they have moſt falſely and maliciouſly aſpers'd me whilſt under my Misfortunes.</p>
            <p>As for my <hi>Religion,</hi> I was brought up in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is eſtabliſh'd by Law, and have ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd it; tho' I confeſs I have been an unworthy Member of it, in not living up to the ſtrict and excellent Rules thereof, for which I take Shame to my ſelf, and humbly ask forgiveneſs of GOD. I come now to dye in that Communion, truſting, as an humble and hearty Penitent, to be receiv'd by the Mercy of God, through the Merits of Jeſus Chriſt my Saviour.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:105818:18"/>
            <p>My <hi>Religion</hi> taught me my <hi>Loyalty,</hi> which, I bleſs God, is untainted: And I have ever endeavour'd, in the ſtation wherein I have been placed, to the utmoſt of my power, to ſupport the Crown of <hi>England</hi> in the True and Lineal Courſe of Deſcent, without interruption.</p>
            <p>As for what I am now to dye; I call God to witneſs, I went not to that Meeting in <hi>Leadenhall-ſtreet</hi> with any ſuch intention, as to invite King <hi>James</hi> by Force to invade this Nation; nor was I my ſelf provided with either Horſe or Arms, or engag'd for any number of Men, or gave particular Conſent for any ſuch Invaſion, as is moſt falſely Sworn againſt me.</p>
            <p>I do alſo declare, in the Preſence of God, That I knew nothing of King <hi>James</hi>'s coming to <hi>Calais,</hi> nor of any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion intended from thence, till it was publickly known: And the only Notion I had that ſomething might be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, was from the <hi>Thoulon</hi> Fleet coming to <hi>Breſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I alſo call God to witneſs, that I receiv'd the knowledge of what is contain'd in thoſe Papers that I gave to a great Man that came to me in the <hi>Tower,</hi> both from Letters and Meſſages that came from <hi>France;</hi> and he told me, when I read them to him, That the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had been acquainted with moſt of thoſe things before.</p>
            <p>I might have expected Mercy from that Prince, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I was inſtrumental in ſaving his Life: For when about <hi>April</hi> 1695, an Attempt form'd againſt him came to my knowledge, I did, partly by Diſſwaſions, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Delays, prevent that Deſign; which, I ſuppoſe, was the reaſon that the laſt Villanous Project was conceal'd from me.</p>
            <p>If there be any Perſons whom I have injur'd in Word or Deed, I heartily pray their Pardon, and beg of God to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105818:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>pardon thoſe who have injur'd me, particularly thoſe who with great Zeal have ſought my Life, and brought the Guilt of my innocent Blood upon this Nation, no Treaſon being prov'd upon me.</p>
            <p>I return my moſt hearty Thanks to thoſe noble and worthy Perſons who gave me their Aſſiſtance, by oppoſing this Bill of Attainder, without which it had been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible I could have fal'n under the Sentence of <hi>Death:</hi> God bleſs them and their Poſterity, tho' I am fully ſatisfied they pleaded their own Cauſe, while they defended mine.</p>
            <p>I pray God to bleſs my true and lawful Soveraign King <hi>James,</hi> the Queen, and the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore him and his Poſterity to this Throne again, for the Peace and Proſperity of this Nation, which is impoſſible to proſper, till the Government is ſettled upon a right Foot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now, O GOD, I do with all humble Devotion com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my Soul into thy Hands, the great Maker and Preſerver of Men, and Lover of Souls, beſeeching thee, that it may be always dear and precious in thy ſight, through the Merits of my Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. FENWICKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
